Does anyone on the committee have
questions for Morgan?
Okay, seeing none,
um, is there any public comment? Is
there anyone who wishes to comment on
this item?
Okay, seeing none, I would call for a
motion.
>> I would move to approve, please.
>> Second.
>> Okay, we have uh Dr. Aldridge mo
motioning to approve and um Councilman
Crave seconding. Seconding,
giving us a second. Um is there any
additional comments from the committee
members?
Okay.
So, um, what is the committee's pleasure
at this point?
I Oh, I'm sorry. I would call for a
vote. I'm sorry. I've been on vacation
for a week. My brain stopped. Um, all
those in favor, please signify by saying
by voting I
>> I
>> any um voting against. Okay. Okay. So,
the recommendation for the public
service or the recommendation from the
public service committee will be to
adopt at the next uh council meeting.
Number 13, Ordinance, third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located south of
West Allison Road, west of Waltershy
Boulevard and north of Grand Harmony
Boulevard from PUB Harmony Plan Unit
development to NR3 neighborhood
residential high density.
Staff report Morgan Dennis Planning and
Development. There have been no changes
to this project and no public comment. I
stand for questions. Okay. Does anyone
have any questions for Morgan?
Okay. Is there any public comment on
this item?
Um, okay. Seeing none,
I would call for a motion.
>> Move to approve.
>> Second.
>> Okay. We have a motion to approve from
Dr. Aldridge and a second from
Councilman Crave. All those in Oh, all
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> Any opposed?
Okay. So, the recommendation from the
public service committee will be to
adopt at the next council meeting.
Number 14, ordinance, third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located north of
Allison Road and west of Waltershy
Boulevard from AG to NR3 neighborhood
residential highdensity.
Staff report. Morgan Dennis, Planning
and Development. There have been no
changes or public comment made about
this project. I stand for questions. Do
we have any questions for Morgan? Oh,
you are getting off easy, girl. Okay.
Any comments from the public?
And no one online, I assume.
Okay.
Um, is there any comments from the
committee? Okay. So then I would call
for a motion.
>> I would move to approve.
>> Second.
>> Okay, we have Dr. Aldridge moving to
approve and uh Councilman Crave
seconding. Um all those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed.
Okay. Um
so the recommendation
the recommendation for the from the
public service committee will be to
adopt at the next approve on third and
final reading. Sorry messed that up.
Number 15, ordinance, third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located
northwest of the intersection of East
29th Street and Central Avenue from MR,
medium density residential to NR2,
neighborhood residential, medium
density.
>> Do we have a staff report?
>> Looks like we do not have
>> I think they might be online. Can you
hold on, share?
Do we have one of the Cheyen Zoom
accounts? You had your hand raised
previously. Would you like to speak?
>> I don't know. Sorry.
>> Is there anyone in the uh that would
like to comment?
Um, Madam Chair, Brad Emmens, AVI, this
is the application to convert the the
central town homes. They're currently
apartments into single owned um
projects. It was two weeks ago. I
haven't heard any additional comments or
anything, but still looking for approval
to the zone change.
>> Any other public comment?
Okay.
Um I would move to approve. Okay.
>> Second.
>> Okay.
>> We have a motion um to approve from Dr.
Aldrich and a second from Councilman
Crave. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I. And those opposed.
Okay. So, the recommendation for the
public service committee will be to
adopt at the next board meeting or the
next council meeting. Number 16,
ordinance, third reading, vacating Frank
Court and a small segment of a
previously vacated alley north of Rock
Spring Street, City of Cheyenne, Larmy
County, Wyoming, located east of North
College Drive and north of Rock Spring
Street.
Do we have a staff report?
Is there anybody online?
Anybody wants to talk to us?
Okay.
>> Raise your hand.
>> Okay. Okay. Mr. Bloom.
>> Charles Bloom. You should be able to
>> chair members of the committee. Charles
Blimp plan development director. I'm
sorry for the delay. I just had my
computer had to be reset on earlier last
week. So everything's like being
reinstalled as I come on here. Um this
item is the vacation of an alley or of a
street rideway Frank Court that is north
of Rock Springs Street. Um what this is
is this is a essentially a roadway that
has never been developed that is
adjacent to a multifamily development
and also um a
uh proposed planning action to the west.
Um it dead ends into dry creek and it
would not be developed. Uh the reason
for this vacation is because the roadway
it just to develop it is not logical nor
feasible for the developer to the uh
east to develop it because of the cost.
Um and it's not logical for the city to
maintain it um in the future because it
would go to nowhere and it would result
in the construction of a of a new uh
bridge over Dry Creek with no real uh
pathway to go. This is a a city
initiated uh vacation of this rightway.
So upon approval of this uh vacation,
what would occur is the land would be
distributed to the east and to the west
um property owners equitably. Um I open
for any questions that you have
regarding this item.
>> Does anyone have any questions? Okay. Is
there any Oh, go ahead. I'm sorry.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Um Mr. Bloom.
I'm looking at the
U
maps and I'm not quite understanding if
this was to
uh go to a single home, how is that
single home going to be accessed after
this is vacated?
>> Mr. Bloom.
>> Yes. Uh chair through to Councilman
Lebornne. Um that is a a great question.
Uh I'm not I believe this is another
project from another planner. They've
been working with the applicant who has
indicated that there would be a driveway
mechanism to get to all properties that
are platted. I do not believe that
single family home um in the back of the
property will exist. Um so I think it
will be a new uh platted rightway or a
dedicated easement to get to all
portions of the site. Um, I can ask our
planners to get you uh some additional
information prior to the meeting on
Monday.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay.
Is there any public comment on this
item?
>> Okay.
>> I move to approve.
>> Second.
>> Okay. We have a a motion to approve by
Dr. Aldrich and a second by uh
Councilman Crave. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed.
Okay.
Number 17, ordinance, second reading,
amending section 13.20.050,
general prohibitions of section
13.20.070,
local limits of chapter 13.20, 20
wastewater treatment and disposal of the
code of the city of Cheyenne, Wyoming to
revise local discharge limits and
related provisions in compliance with
the MPDes
and the WPDES
permit requirements.
>> Hey, we have a staff report.
>> Yes, Madam Chair, Matt Buer, Shine,
Board of Public Utilities, Water
Recation Division Manager. So, in a
nutshell, what this is is every time
that we get a a discharge permit update
at both of our facilities, the Dry Creek
or Crow Creek, we are required through
the EPA to do what they call local
limits study. Um, think of as the PI. It
just gives each industry in town um the
allowance to discharge um their
materials to us and also doesn't allow
hazardous materials to come into our
facility that we can't treat that would
harm um downstream users. Um if this is
approved today um through the council,
it will go to the EPA for a uh public
comment period through Wyman Tribune
Eagle. Happy to answer any questions.
>> Do we have questions? Uh Dr. Aldridge.
>> Yes. Uh Dr. Mr. U. So as I'm looking
through this documentation that you
provided, it looks as if are are and
this is my question. Are our local
limits lower than the EPA
um limits or their recommendations? It
looks like according to page 95 of the
local limits evaluation attachment G
where we've got lined out the daily
maximum discharge limits and the total
maximum allowable um that I don't see a
on the sheet that I see
on page 98 which I believe replaces that
is that am I am I reading that right
that the daily maximum discharge would
increase from what was 031
for for instance arsenic
um to being 106 at the dry creek water
reclamation facility
>> through you madam chair so those are our
old local limits um so that's going off
what the old old uh study pro provided
for us with the recent kind of change in
Holly Frontier opened up a lot of
different limits to other folks and it
also made a little bit bigger for them
if you look at copper copper down came
down just a little bit and then certain
parameters did come up because you don't
have that one industry taking the
majority of the pie so it did open it up
to a bit of the resting the industries
in town.
>> Followup question. So I just want to
make sure that I'm understanding. So
based upon
what's being processed at these rec
water reclamation facilities
um and what the allowable limits are by
the EPA are our limits that we're using
and are outlined here. And it's
milligrams per liter I'm guessing,
right? that those are um higher, lower
or the same as the EPA.
>> Oh, we got so what our local limits are
is we through Madam Chair, sorry. Um
we'll actually set the local limits. We
send it off to the EPA and they'll
they'll consider approvable. So they
actually look at our limits based on
what our our max allowable head limits
headwork limits are coming in and then
that was what sets the the discharge
permit for going forward of what's going
into the creek. So limits that we set
are for us only and that's why every
municipality has to set their own local
limit. So Port Collins arsenic level is
going to be different from ours
depending on what their plan is able to
to with with hand with hold and stand.
Um so it'll be different. It's not just
an EPA requirement. It's them looking at
it and what our what our treatment
process is, what we're able to um treat
at the facilities themselves.
>> One more follow-up question. Sorry.
Absolutely. So, um, Chairwoman Emmansu,
so
we look at then what our water naturally
contains and then we also look at what's
being um put out by industry. So, for
instance, on page 100 where it talks
about fats, oils, and grease, the
maximum limit is milligrams, 100
milligrams per liter. Is that per
establishment?
>> Three, madam chair. It's what our our
facilities can handle.
>> Okay. Yep.
>> Okay. So,
the facility can handle that. I'm sorry.
Follow up the question through based on
if every let's say that every restaurant
in town decides to discharge
>> um grease and fat and oil in their
water. Um, if every entity did that,
as long as it didn't uh um exceed 100
milligrams per liter, our facilities
could handle it,
>> but we don't really have that kind of
control. So,
>> you madam chair, you're absolutely
right. Yes. That's why we So, Vickiy's
back there. She's the compliance
supervisor. Um, her staff is the IP
division as well or the department. So,
they're the ones that go out and check
the restaurants for their their fats,
oil, and greases. grease traps and
>> the grease traps are grease interceptors
um and also the industries um and then
OWS's oral water separator so that does
play a part in this her staff is the
also one to answer your first question
is they do go out and we'll test for
local limits sampling at our facilities
and that's where our consultant they're
online right now um that's where they
get their numbers from and they see
exactly what's coming to the plant what
our plant can handle and what it was
designed for
>> one last sorry one last question
>> so is what we're able to handle through
our uh water recommend facilities um
pretty similar to what you would find in
other communities
>> of our size.
>> Three, madam chair. So it's actually a
little bit more stringent because of
what we discharge to is the actual crow
creek since we make up the majority of
the creek itself. We don't have the plat
like Colorado has discharging to a big
body of water. Um so our like our
selenium for instance is 5 UGL. That's
actually lower than what the drinking
water standard is. So our our limits are
very very strict here because of what we
discharge to and the body of water that
we discharge to. Thank you.
>> Yeah, absolutely. Thank you.
>> Any other questions? Thank you.
>> Yep. Absolutely.
>> Any questions from public?
Okay.
Hearing none or any comments, I'm sorry,
from the public.
Okay. Hearing none.
What's your
>> move to approve?
>> Second.
>> Okay. We have a motion to approve from
Dr. Aldridge and a second from
Councilman Crave. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I.
>> I I.
>> And those opposed.
>> Okay. So, the recommendation uh from the
public service committee will be to
approve at the next council meeting on
second reading.
>> Number 18, ordinance, second reading,
amending section 2.76.040,
040 designation of downtown development
district of chapter 2.76 downtown
development authority of title 2
administration and personnel of the
municipal code of the city of Cheyenne
Wyoming to expand the downtown
development district.
>> Do do you have a presentation?
>> Hey and we have a staff report.
Good afternoon. Sophia Maize, downtown
development executive director. For the
record
as I bring up the map to show you all,
this is a
following ordinance from the resolution
that the governing body passed on
February 23rd, 2026.
And we do have the representative for
the applicant online as well if you'd
like to hear from him.
On November 18th, 2025, staff received
the petition from Raul Dami,
representative of the property owners of
21 2100 Snyder Avenue for inclusion of
property within the downtown development
district. This property is contiguous to
the downtown district boundary along
Snyder Avenue.
I assume it's not working.
The inclusion of this property uh would
include all adjacent rights of way
including but not limited to Snyder
Avenue on the east side, West 21st
Street on the south side, and the
adjacent alley on the north side. This
would allow DDA funds to be used on
improvements within the adjacent rights
of way as well as to collect mill levy
from the property.
Uh, as I've stated before with the prior
resolution, this the inclusion of this
property will advance the DDA statutory
purpose to prevent blight and support
property values within the downtown
core. Expanding the district would also
allow targeted infrastructure and
property improvements through existing
DDA programs, improving functionality
and visual appeal while supporting
private investment.
This inclusion adds to the 2024 downtown
plan of development to help stimulate
economic activity, attract new
businesses, and support job creation,
particularly in light of the potential
implementation of the Reed Rail project,
or at least the activation of properties
along this corridor and the increased
demand that is expected to be generated
for nearby properties. Additionally,
this expansion of the district adds to
the opportunity for future collaboration
along the Snyder Avenue corridor,
strengthening the West Edge
revitalization efforts, advancing
Brownfield mitigation, and reinforcing a
key gateway into downtown Cheyenne for
I25.
At its regular board meeting on January
15th, 2026, the DDA board recommended
approval of the petition to include this
property in the district boundaries. And
on February 23rd, 2026, the Cheyenne
governing body adopted the resolution
6514 upon second and final reading
expressing the support of the governing
body for the inclusion of this property.
DDA staff recommends approval of the
ordinance amending section 2.76041,
excuse me, 2.76.040
um to expand the downtown development
district. And as I said, the
representative uh for the petitioners is
here today on Zoom if you have any
questions. Thank you. Okay. Are there
any questions for Sophia? Yes, ma'am.
Dr. Aldridge.
>> Chairwoman Emmens through you. Um
I I first and foremost I really
appreciate this. It's this is contiguous
because we've seen things that are not
where people are wanting to be added to
the DDA. I am curious though
how
how much further we can expand and
continue to call this the downtown core.
And secondly, I'm very concerned about
the open container laws that we now have
for the DDA area being extended clear
over to Snyder and and the ability of
our law enforcement to be able to uh
keep a handle on what's going on with
open containers.
>> Go ahead, Sophia.
Um, Madame Chair, was there a
>> Yeah. a question?
>> Yes.
>> How are what at what point is this no
longer downtown core? And how are you
going to make sure that we're able to
actually implement
um the laws that we have governing the
downtown
development authority area for open
container clear over on Snyder?
>> Madam Chair, uh that is a very good
question, the two-part question. I do
know that the original downtown district
did extend I believe clear to Missile
Drive at one point. Um it was very
expansive and was reduced because of
that concern of the ability to manage.
Um that is a question for my board that
I would need them to answer as well as
the uh the commercial property owners of
the downtown district. However, Snyder
Avenue is contiguous to a very big
catalyst project in our plan of
development. So, for that catalyst
project of Reed Rail, for that to border
the downtown boundary as it does um is
helpful to the rest of downtown. But the
effects the the positive effects of that
catalyst project could be expanded to
Snider and potentially even um the uh
forgive me, the other street that's down
to that way. Um,
Snyder Avenue from looking at it, it is
uh majority residential. So to have a
lot of those properties uh residential
and church or religious and so to have a
lot of those properties integrated into
the DDA is probably not a factor in the
near future. Um, however, we do have the
pump house which is on Snyder Avenue
which is contiguous to the DDA district.
um that we have Pump House Park that's a
catalyst project but not the pump house
itself. So that could be an opportunity.
Um in terms of how far do we expand and
when we
create our own limit, I believe
personally and professionally that
Snyder would be an appropriate limit. Um
the character of Snyder Avenue is
supports the West Edge revitalization
efforts. Um but anything west of that is
kind of starting to go into more
industrial. Um in terms of the
open container law, that is something
that will need to be coordinated with
with um our police department and our
fire department as well. I cannot speak
to that in terms of the safety.
>> Dr. Aldridge, do you have any other
questions?
>> No, I'm I'm good. Thanks.
>> Okay.
>> There any other questions for Sophia?
Okay, thank you. Is there any public
comment either in the room or online?
Okay.
How do you say his name?
>> Raul Dami. You should be able to speak
if you'd like to.
>> Um, yeah. Can you guys hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. I mean, I I don't have much to
add. Um like like Sophia said, the open
container law um quite honestly I don't
know if I'm you know capable of speaking
to that per se. Um I can speak for my
family uh for our business. Uh we've
been running it for you know 30 plus
years now. Um it's right on the edge of
the border right now. We want to be part
of the DDA. We want to expand our
business. We want to make it um if I can
say this nicely, we want to make it
nicer. um you know, we want to be a part
of the story for the West Edge
revitalization. Uh so that was the
reasoning for us to put forth this um
request. Um we've been there for a
while. We've been there and we've been
in the community, like I said, for 30
years. Um so really from our side, it
was more just, you know, we want to be
part of the story. Um and we want to do
our part to help, you know, grow that
area. And that's really all I got to
add. Um thank you.
Thank you. Any other public comment?
Okay.
Um, Councilman Lebornne,
>> thank you. Um, I'm not quite sure how to
pronounce your name, sir, but uh
>> that's fine.
having uh
bought gas there when you sold gas and
many other things at your store. Um I'm
very familiar with it and I fully
support this action so that you can
hopefully take advantage of the good
improvements going to be coming to that
area soon.
>> Yeah. Um my question is and and you
noticed that in this uh paperwork here
we talked about blight and um certainly
um I'm just curious are you currently
utilizing that metal building uh just
north of your store that was a car wash
at one time. Is that in use?
>> Um as of today it is not in use. Well, I
know this isn't part of the approval
process, but I would suggest that
>> uh maybe you ought to take a look at uh
>> yeah,
>> demolishing it. I mean, I think there
are a lot of uh factors like that in
that old part of town
>> that if we could just bit by bit um get
rid of them, it would help. But I uh I
certainly support this. I think it's
appropriate. Uh, I don't think expanding
the district uh is all that great in a
lot of cases, but uh the lack of a
grocery on the west side is a serious
matter and I'm certainly would want to
see your family continue and hopefully
thrive in that area. Thank you.
>> Yeah, and just so I can add to that, um,
that is definitely part of the plan.
I've reached out to a couple
construction companies in Cheyenne and
gotten quotes on essentially like
remodeling our building or even, you
know, expanding it. Um, so if we were to
do that, that um that structure that
today is not being used will come down.
Um, point taken that, you know, we
should probably just go ahead and do
that um just for cleansiness and appeal
of said property. Um, but that's
definitely part of our plan.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Mhm. Any other public comment?
Okay,
Dr. Aldrich.
>> Oh, I'm sorry. I thought you were had a
question.
>> I did have a question. Okay, go ahead. I
heard a comment. Um, I am going to be
voting in support of this. Anytime we
have a business owner who's wanting to
basically tax themselves in order to
participate
um in a program that we have. Um, I
think that that's um appreciated for
sure and I think that it does make sense
on the west um edge off of Snyder to
include this um probably more so than
even some of our folks that we include
over on the south side um of the
district quite honestly. Um, but I I I'm
I um do have share some concerns that we
just want to make sure that um we're not
bringing people into the district only
because of what they can access as far
as grants. Um so appreciate you're
wanting to provide a service and to
participate in the downtown development
authority as a full member um and with
all that that entails.
>> Okay.
So I would call for a motion
>> and move to approve.
>> Second.
>> So it's moved by Dr. Aldrich, seconded
by Councilman uh Lebornne. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I. I.
>> And those opposed.
Uh the recommendation for the public
service committee will be to adopt at
the council meeting.
Number 21 resolution authorizing the
mayor and city clerk to sign a final
plat for 2900 central avenue town homes
city of Cheyenne Larmy County Wyoming
live northwest of the intersection of
East 29th Street and Central Avenue and
do we have a staff report
>> chair and members of the committee
counter white planning development
department and apologies for missing my
first couple of items I got stuck on the
phone upstairs about a project on
tonight's agenda for planning commission
um with this plat Uh this goes along
with one of the earlier items with the
zone change. Um all they're doing with
this plat is basically taking that
property that is all town houses uh
currently in the way they are built and
putting each unit on its own individual
lot uh and then also subdividing out the
garages. So each townhouse has a garage
as well off the alley and then having a
common area. Um this basically goes and
into the UDC as a cottage lot style of
development. So a site plan has been
submitted for the common area which is
just basically our way of kind of
notating what is there what's in the
common area and um having that on file
to show that it is cottage plots. Um so
that's what this plat is doing. each uh
unit will be basically on its own
individual property can be sold off
individually and then the common open
space would be under an HOA
and I am available um this was
recommended for approval by planning
commission um at their
oh we're on April so it would have been
March uh meeting at this point because
we did have to delay the uh plat for the
zone change um but they did recommend
approval staff does recommend approval I
am available for questions
Okay, questions, Mr. Secret,
I'm sorry.
>> Thank you. Um, so
those town homes have been there for
quite a while
>> and I just assume they were under the
ownership of those individuals who uh
had that property. So,
in the past when they were sold, um the
the land didn't come with it. They I
mean, how does that work? I mean, it's
been that way for many years. And, uh I
sometimes they seem like they'd be up
for sale and get sold. And I'm just
curious how this new um zoning and
platting here, what difference it makes.
chair through you. Um, so my
understanding is that they probably
weren't sold. They might have been
rented. Um, because right now currently
they are technically all on a single lot
uh under one ownership. So one person
owns that entire property, owns all the
units uh rents out the units. So with
this, it basically changes that entire
thing to now each unit can be sold off
individually. um at least I hope they
weren't sold off individually
previously. Um because they definitely
wouldn't have come with land or really
with anything cuz they're not even
condoed. Um so my belief would be that
they would have been just rented. Uh so
this plat does actually change it to now
they could be sold off individually. So
now somebody can actually own their unit
and then basically they have the common
open space.
>> Thank you. Any other questions for Mr.
White? Okay. Any other public or any
public comments?
Okay. Hearing none.
>> I would move to approve.
>> Okay.
>> Second.
>> So, it's been approve been mo moved by
um Dr. Aldridge, seconded by Councilman
um Crrave. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed.
Okay. So the recommendation from the
public service committee will be to
adopt at the next council meeting.
Number 22, resolution approving and
adopting the city of Cheyenne crosswalk
criteria and guidelines and confirming
the authority of the city engineer to
implement crosswalk treatments.
>> And we have a staff report. Good
afternoon, Madame Chair and members of
the committee. I'm Rick Aean, city
traffic engineer, and uh Tom Cobb, I
believe, is online if there's any
questions that I can't answer that uh he
could provide. Um this uh staff report
is for a resolution to implement a
crosswalk criteria and guideline for the
city of Cheyenne. um nothing like that
currently exists. So we rely on the
MUTCD to follow and that's kind of what
most communities in our state as well as
Y dot do. But those numbers are very
high and don't work well for smaller
communities even though you know for
Wyoming we have a larger community but
still doesn't work very well. So, this
document, um, Jennifer, if you'll go to
slide two, um, that's just kind of I'll
kind of give an overview for for the the
some of these slides. This document is
to establish a resolution to provide a
city standard that better meets the
needs of the community rather than
following that MUTCD standard. That's a
manual on uniform traffic control
devices. And that's a national standard
that most people uh try to follow, but
it's it's it's really high for a
crosswalk.
It requires like 100 pedestrians in an
hour. And we we we that just doesn't
work. You know, anybody can see that
doesn't work for a community like ours.
Um so this this document is going to
serve a purpose to improve our
pedestrian safety and ensure consistency
which is very important in implementing
treatments across the city. If you'll go
to the next slide, Jennifer.
Um, this here is a flowchart that we had
a consultant help us put together that
is going to be the criteria that we plan
to um hopefully adopt and follow to give
us good consistency and uh data support
that we can very easily or much easier
say yes and no when we get requests for
crosswalks.
Um the requirements that you'll that you
can kind of go through on this include
um sight distance. That's very important
to have good sight distance when when we
have a request for a crosswalk location.
Um we want to have minimum crosswalk
spacing. Um we don't want a whole bunch
of crosswalks requested, you know, block
after block after block. And if we
implement devices out there, they become
less compliant for people to abide, you
know. So the criteria is very important
for that. Um, and down at the bottom,
we've also got a time frame for how we
would implement this. Some things can be
implemented very easily within months.
you know, if we if it's just crosswalk
markings and signing and those kind of
things, but if we've got to design
something and it has some complications
like storm sewer drains and we want to
add curb extensions, those things take a
lot more time to design and can take one
to two years, you know, so we've got to
get a consultant on board and go through
a a pretty lengthy process.
Um if you go to the next slide there. Um
now this shows the treatment levels that
we um with the consultant came up with
to apply towards the data that we would
um obtain anywhere from not you know
implementing any kind of treatment if
there are less than 20 pedestrians. 20
pedestrians is the criteria that we are
using as opposed to the 100 in a peak
hour what which was from the MUTCD.
The 20 is what you typically use for
your school crossings. So, we thought
that would be a good place for us to
start with this and try to be consistent
with and, you know, as we get some more
pedestrian crosswalk requests in,
that may be something that we adjust as
we go forward, but it's kind of a a
balance with everything. You can't put
too many devices out there. So, that's
why the criteria is important. Um, I
mean, for example, we put too many uh
rectangular rapid flash and beacon
systems out there that activate and
flash,
they could become almost like I mean,
we've got so much signing out there that
it becomes road noise. So, you know,
there's a balance with all of that.
Um so the the treatment levels that are
identified here go from um standard
markings and crossing uh signing and
then the rectangular rapid flash and
beacon system would be the next highest
step um depending on what the risk is to
the pedestrians. And then there's also
the pedestrian hybrid beacon which used
to be called the hawk system. Those are
some of the ones that we installed
recently in the last couple years at on
Persing um where Bags is and then we
installed one on McCormick. Um those are
more critical when we get to corridors
that have multi-lanes.
Um even though we did install the Hawk
system at um there at McCormack, there
was um a fatality there. So, you know,
it kind of kind of bumped up how we were
going to treat that. But, you know, if
there wasn't a fatality there, we
probably would have just installed the
the RRFB there and probably would have
been just as as well served. Um, we've
got bumpouts or curb extensions there as
well that limits the the distance that
people have to cross the roads too. And
so, those are important. you know, if
we've got parking lanes where we are
going to install treatments, we would
probably look at doing curb extensions
in those cases, too. There's a couple in
town. Um, one that comes to mind that we
need to look at probably installing some
curb extensions on, if any of you are
familiar with Story Boulevard at uh,
Marshall Road. Um, it's a school
crossing there and it's Story's pretty
wide there and we really need to make
that safer for kids and in the next safe
routes to school project
will uh, install curb extensions there.
Um so as I mentioned with this being the
the first effort to kind of standardize
uh this crosswalk criteria we'll
engineering department will continue to
evaluate um any requests that come in
and even you know uh other places that
we know there may be a need and we'll
look at even trying to adjust this
criteria as we go forward. Um I
recommend adoption of the revol
resolution for improved pedestrian
safety and consistency of device
implementation implementations that are
data given driven that that being data
driven is very critical rather than just
um more political pressure.
Um I'm available for any questions.
>> Okay, Dr. Aldridge,
Chairwoman through you. So, in a typical
school zone,
um, and I'm thinking about, um, we've
had a couple that have been brought to
our attention lately, uh, 12th and, uh,
12th Street, which runs through Sun
Valley along the Sunrise Park there.
um that according to this it's uh the
speed limit is
um 30 miles per hour um through that
area and it's a two-lane street. So
according to this
this um chart that you gave us, we're
looking at that nothing would be
uh recommended at that location because
it's less than 1500 vehicles and um is
that and that's a daily number, correct?
>> Correct.
>> Is so is that accurate? Am I reading
this chart correctly?
um through through you, Madame Chair. Uh
I don't know um what the volumes are on
that road, but we do treat uh crosswalks
in association with schools differently,
too. So, we're we're not using this to
drive what we're doing around schools.
This is
>> okay.
>> Beyond schools. So where in this packet
because I don't see anywhere where it
talks about exceptions for schools.
It talks about decorating crosswalks
which I found interesting but it doesn't
talk about
any exceptions around schools. Is there
is am I missing it in here
>> through you chair? Uh we didn't address
schools because they're a separate
entity.
Um, so it might be something that we
need to see about addressing.
I'm just thinking if we're going to
chairwoman Emmens, if we're going to
pass take the time and the energy and
the effort to pass a crosswalk criteria
and guidelines and we know that our
largest concerns in our by community
members is usually around schools, we
might want to include some sort of at
least acknowledgement or paragraph that
talks about that we're doing something
different in school zones than we are um
in other areas. U one more follow-up
question. Go ahead, Chairwoman Emmens.
My uh second question is around
materials for crosswalks. Um, I think
that most of us recognize that in a low
volume area, painting the crosswalk
works perfectly well. But in some of our
higher traffic areas, doing the plastic
heat applied markings, I don't know what
you really call those, but basically the
ironons,
um, is
um, probably more desirable. But I don't
see anywhere in here where it talks
about um materials for marking again
other than it talks about markings and
signs, but it doesn't really talk about
um the actual materials for marking. Um
again, except for when we talk about
that we don't like decorative
crosswalks.
>> You're madam chair again. Um, so
trying to think how to Could you repeat
the question again? Just
>> is there a place where we could also
include um talking about materials based
on traffic volume?
>> Okay. with with regard to the materials.
So, um
that has been kind of uh addressed by
the person that's been in the traffic
engineering position. Prior to me, the
traffic engineer like to paint
everything thinking that there could be
money savings and those kind of things.
I'm not a big fan of painting anything.
I am in the process of basically
putting thermoplastic that's what the
the ones that are called that um are
basically heat applied.
I would like to basically replace
anything that's been painted out there
with thermoplastic because there is such
a long duration that those don't have to
be reapplied.
um on a local road they may last 5 10
years where the paint is uh the
especially the reflectivity goes away
within months a lot of times if there's
much for traffic
>> snow plows
>> yeah so so it's it's kind of been up to
the decision of the traffic engineer in
the past
um but we could certainly entertain you
know making that a city standard so that
that is not so subject objective to
who's in a position. So, I like that.
>> Dr. Aldridge,
>> um I see that HDR is the one who
actually did this report, but I would
like to see those two things addressed
because um I think you've hit the nail
on the head with consistency. It's hard
to be consistent when we have turnover
and turn in the engineers's office. And
hopefully that doesn't happen very
often, but we know it does. And it would
be nice to have something a document
when we have somebody come in that can
follow that for consistency sake and
it's not left up to an individual's
discretion. So thank you.
>> Yeah, through you madam chair. I I
completely agree with that and that's
why we're to begin with starting going
forward with something like this to
create consistent standards that the
city can use going forward not just now
but in the future.
>> Councilman Leborn.
>> Thank you. Um thank you Mr. Aean. Uh
obviously this is something that um some
of us and I think I can particularly
refer to uh the other me council members
who are on the traffic and safety
committee um are very glad to see I'm
glad to see it's a work in progress and
we're probably going to be able to uh
evaluate all the different situations
that arise and get away from those
ridiculous
uh high counts that were never
realistic.
I did want to follow up a little bit on
the question of thermal plastic
markings. Um we have so many uh I was
out at uh Dell Range in Yellowstone on
my bike yesterday and uh those markings
crossing over to the uh golf course are
just gone. And so I mean we're going to
have to play a lot of catchup I think
first of all and uh that's something to
look at in terms of the budget adoption
as coming up here because uh that was
really a very um
misguided effort to
rely on paint and uh so I look forward
to uh working with you and your
department. And I know I I have examples
that uh I'm very interested in and uh I
think that this is uh uh give some
substance to it. I see that we have a
representative here from the mayor's
council for people with disabilities and
as the council representative to that
group I applaud this effort. I think we
can do a lot better. And of course that
gets into ancillary issues like timing,
light timing and uh where you have I
mean there just a lot of different uh
different considerations. So I
particularly look forward to hearing
about um
the issues of the point park that I
expect are going to be uh discussed here
shortly. So I hope we can um go to some
of the more controversial and in my
opinion necessary
projects and and and reach some
understanding that obviously in some
cases like 8 and Carry there's going to
be some expense in terms of those curb
extensions but um all this attention to
this is certainly warranted and I
appreciate your efforts. Thank you,
>> Councilman Crap.
>> Madam Chair, through you. Um, Mr.
Raymond.
It's on.
I'll get it right in here. How's that?
Is that better? Thank you, Jennifer.
Birthday girl. Anyways, um, Mr. Aman,
Councilman Lebourne brought up the Point
Park. Uh, we have neighborhood reps
here. Can you give us an update on if
that area now qualifies for a crosswalk?
Uh I believe we were looking at uh
Gardinia and
Whispering Hills. Is that correct? Will
that now qualify under these uh
standards for some type of treatment
>> through you, Madam Chair? Yes. um the
the two crosswalks out of this study
that we have that we will be um putting
together designs and implementation. One
being Gardinia and Whispering Hills. We
evaluated two other locations uh near
the Point Park on each end of that park
and those numbers were like in the
single digits at peak times. We will
continue to evaluate those. Um it'll be
important to see when we get that
location, the devices installed at
Whispering Hills
that we are able to get people to start
using that location rather than at the
ends. But we will continue to evaluate
those other ends. that and part part of
the things that make those other two
locations on the ends of the park not
very viable besides
um not meeting the pedestrian volumes is
there's curvature to the road
horizontally and vertically at both of
those locations at the ends of the park.
And you know the the thought process be
behind the roadway designers was good to
slow people down when you create those
kind of curvatures to the roadway but it
doesn't contribute to the safety of
pedestrians very well. So we we will
continue to evaluate those other
locations as well. Um the other one that
also came up was at 8 and Kerry. That's
one of those ones that's going to take
more substantial design because we've
got storm sewer drains and we've got to
build curb extensions there to actually
make that a a safe safer place for
pedestrians across. If we were to
install the rectangular rapid flash and
beacons to the existing facility out
there, it would be very difficult to
make that ADA compliant for one thing
because the sidewalks currently are only
4T wide, at least on the the souththeast
corner, and there's that property owner
on that corner has some very nice
vegetation there. And for us to make it
ADA compliant, we'd have to tear a lot
of that stuff out. And so we're better
served to do curb extensions than go
down that route. And there there's a an
advantage to doing the curb extensions
by shortening up the distance for the
pedestrians to cross and making them
more visible when they're getting out
there preparing to cross as well. I'm
sure follow
>> um one other comment I just wanted to
kind of follow up on with uh Councilman
Lelay. He mentioned uh Yellowstone and
uh Del Ranch. Um, part of the reason
those markings haven't been updated to
with thermoplastic is we have a a
project in the works to upgrade that
whole signalized intersection. And so it
doesn't make sense to spend that kind of
money to do that. Now, if they're
getting in bad shape, we'll just have to
paint those to kind of limp by till we
let that in in a couple years.
>> Councilman Crave,
>> one quick followup. Uh now that we've
um determined that uh Gardinia and
Whispering Hills is uh treatable, uh a
rough timeline for the folks that are
here, please. Through you, Madam Chair.
Um yeah, sorry, I meant to follow up
with that. We're looking at a time frame
to get that designed and implemented um
sometime later this summer. Um I've got
a safe routes to school project that
trying to get let right now. um going to
I'm hoping to get a contractor on board
once that job is awarded cuz it'll be a
contract that I can um just get quotes
on from three contractors and get it out
um fairly quickly and get that
constructed this summer with the safe
routes to school project.
>> Any other uh Councilman Lebornne?
>> Thank you. Uh well, Mr. Aman, I
appreciate your comment about uh Bill
Range in Yellowstone. However, um
I'm not sure what the process is. Um
certainly of the painting of the
crosswalk and I understand that probably
it is a immediate need of the
thermoplastic. I'm not sure how long
it's going to be before that project is
um underway and completed, but perhaps
uh those of us that are concerned about
these matters, and I'm not saying it
belongs in these standards, but it
belongs in in your office to where
people can really um bring forward
problems as we've seen happen to
initiate this entire process. test. But,
uh, there there's a number of situations
that would definitely benefit from
either the painting or the
thermoplastic.
And so, it's uh um I certainly look
forward to discussing that with you. And
uh I raised that question of uh that
location because
I think it's difficult to measure
pedestrian and bicycle
crossings at various locations. I mean
automobiles are easier but uh some of
these are and that one in particular um
I use regularly as well as a lot of
other people. So, I'd sure like to see
it uh painted as soon as possible. Thank
you,
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Chairwoman Emmens, um your comments made
it brought two more questions to mind,
Mr. Amon. Um can you tell us where the
safe school route project is that you're
working on?
>> True, Madam Chair. It's been um in the
purchasing office to let for some time
and I'm just waiting for it to get
advertised.
>> Oh, no. Not not that kind of where is it
at in the process, but where physically
is it in our community?
>> Oh, the locations. Sorry.
>> Um, so um
you probably don't recall, but we we
went through the council process to
approve that project at one point, but
so it was um Alta Vista for the most
part. Um there's a lot of upgrades that
will get done there because it's
lacking. Um even crosswalks on 16th and
17th Street on the north and south side
of the schools will upgrade um the
crossing out at 17th all the markings.
Um, one of the things that
um, as the traffic engineer that I feel
is important
um, to go forward with for consistency
purposes and safety of our students
normally at our crosswalks.
So, so a normal school zone has the
flashing beacons saying, "Oh, you got to
slow down to 20 mph going through here."
But when you get to the crosswalk,
other than the signing that's there and
the crosswalk markings, there really
isn't anything there to get people's
attention. So,
as a standard going forward, I'm going
to be implementing the um rapid flashing
beacon systems at the actual crosswalks.
So, a kid has to push the button, it'll
activate those flashing beacons and get
people's attention better.
One more question. Go ahead. Um, the ETH
and Kerry bumpout project that you're
talking about
>> in light of the um movement last week in
order to fund the bridge over I25 for
Frontier Days. Do you do you really
think that there's still the traffic
foot traffic counts that would justify
um bumpouts at ETH and Carry
>> through you, Madam Chair? Um I think
just um outside of frontier days the
counts at 8 and Kerry were above the 20.
Okay.
>> And so that's mostly just residents
going and using the park greenway and
all of that. And um we actually
um have
another location mid um midway between
Kerry and Central at Pioneer. It's I
think midway between those intersections
that we're looking at implementing uh
radar rapid flashing beacon system there
too. um the numbers from the counts that
we had didn't meet 20, but we're going
to design that for now because um
especially come frontier days, it may be
worth having that there at that
location.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay, any other questions? Thank you,
Mr. Amon.
Is there any public comment either in
the room or online? Madame Chair, um,
Engineer Cobb has had his hand raised
multiple times, so I just want to check,
can we check with him to see if he has
anything you'd like to add to the
presentation?
>> Thanks, Jennifer. I I don't I just I I
guess I I wanted to make one comment to
Dr. Aldridge just to make sure we were
clear moving forward. So I, you know,
really the purpose of the document is to
create this avenue for folks to be able
to to inquire about crosswalks and other
devices at normal corners. What what I
wanted to add to the statement about the
school zone, I don't think it's
appropriate to put it in this particular
document. I think we should let MUTCD
handle the school zones and the school
particulars. Um, that technology and
things change quite a bit. um meaning we
have on a federal level we examine these
with all over the country. So this this
this particular guideline is not
intended for schools. It it should be it
should be treated separately. We can
certainly put a paragraph in that states
we will address it according to national
standards and if we if we need to add
additional it's it's engineering
judgment based on our own area. Um
secondly I would add to Mr. Lelay's
comment about the materials and I think
yours as well. Um again this is a guide
document for installation. Those those
particular about material types should
be put in our standard specifications
which we do do. So it's a separate
document ma'am.
>> Yes.
>> Uh chairwoman for you to Mr. Cobb. Um, I
would appreciate at least uh some
acknowledgement of how school zones are
being handled in this report so that
when someone does request what our
standard operating procedures are or our
policies are on crosswalks that that is
um at least referred at least refers
them to um the MUTC that you you
referenced. Thank you,
>> Madam Chair through through you to Dr.
Al. We certainly can do that, ma'am.
>> Okay. Thank you. Any other comments
online or in the room?
Madame Chairman, council members, Bonnie
Cruz, live at the Point Twin Homes and
following the discussions of the
crosswalk for whispering hills in
Gardinia.
Uh it's brought up about the number of
people that do cross. I would like to
know if it has been considered going
both east and west on Gardinia, not in a
big giddy up pickup, but a smaller car.
The blind spots that you see and the
people crossing in these where you are
at these blind spots and come over the
hill.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
>> Okay. Thank you. Uh, Mr. Aman, do you
know the answer to that
>> through you, Madam Chair? I'm not sure
I'm following with exactly where you're
asking for additional crosswalks or
implementation.
Are you are you talking about the side
streets that like like to cross
whispering hills there um going east and
westbound instead of across to the park
>> east and westbound there are blind spots
>> as you come over several excuse me there
going both east and west on Gardinia
from Yellowstone or Powderhouse each way
there are blind spots spots and people
crossing that if you're driving you
don't see them.
And I am not sure if the council and Mr.
Eman if you are aware there was a young
boy about 10 years old that was hit by a
truck there I believe on uh Bolard in
Gardinia
and that in that area it was because he
couldn't see around the car. The kid
came out behind the car. So, it's a it's
a pretty um
welltraveled road as you know. Uh lot of
lot of uh pedestrians, a lot of older
people from the Point Twin Homes,
including myself and my husband who uses
a walker at 92. And he's not as fast
crossing Gardine as he used to be when
he was 60. And I do think that some of
these items should be taken under
consideration.
I would like personally if possible say
Mr. Aean uh council members
draw driving on Gardinia like I say not
in a big pickup truck but in the normal
little sedan that most people drive and
consider these blind spots. They are
there.
Okay. Any questions?
Thank you, Madam Chairman, council
members.
>> Okay. Any other public comments?
>> All right. Committee, what is your
>> I would move to approve.
>> Second.
>> Okay. We have um Dr. Aldridge has moved
and uh Councilman uh Lebornne has
seconded. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I. Oh, yep. Go ahead,
sir.
>> Thank you. Um,
this is a part of a
change in our culture and our roadway
design. I think that Gardinia was never
built or intended to be the kind of a
feeder that it is to the point and
that's really and same thing with 12th
Street. um they were done that way and I
think we can try to find some
improvements and I and hopefully look at
roadway design uh in a different light
over in the future of the city because
uh getting to the other side of town as
fast as possible is really not the goal.
And I think all of this should be
considered in light of our adoption of
the vision zero goals for uh um
aiming at a decrease in pedestrian and
bicycle deaths. So this is a step. It's
it's important step. I'm glad to uh to
be able to use this because obviously
uh particularly when we looked at
Gardinia and the Point Park. Um
I applaud the neighbors for sticking
with this. Um you're getting probably
not exactly what uh would be optimum in
your mind, but it's a heck of a lot
better than it was. And not only that,
you helped the entire city.
Your persistence
um really helped bring this uh to where
we got this document. And so you're not
only helping your neighborhood, you're
helping uh the entire city. And I think
that uh those of us that share these
concerns and use those crosswalks,
uh there's a there's a lot of factors
here. I I believe that we need to uh
really look at and enforce
uh those fines for the forvoiding a
crosswalk. I mean, I've been right there
standing there and they come right by
and I'm like, "Wait a minute, that's a
very serious thing." And and I've never
agreed or believed it's appropriate the
idea that installing a crosswalk could
lead to more danger and more accidents.
um and the people would believe that
that traffic control device um was any
less than a light or anything else. I
mean, if those devices are there,
they're there for a reason. And we've
got a long long way to go before we do
anything unnecessary because we've got a
lot of necessary efforts to catch up
with. But again, uh, thank you to the
dedicated effort of that neighborhood
because, uh, and of course, I think
that's part of it, too. Uh, people have
to use them. It it is, uh, sometimes I
find myself jaywalking when I shouldn't,
and I think that we all need to be aware
that the pedestrian, the bicyclist have
a real responsibility.
Um, and as traffic changes, I think that
we're on the right track. So, thank you.
>> Okay,
everyone. Um,
in support of the sorry, support of the
resolution, please signify by saying I
>> I
>> opposed.
Uh the recommendation of the public
service committee will be to adopt at
the next meeting of the city council.
With that conclusion of our business, we
are adjourned. Thank you all and